Black Mirror: Bandersnatch is a science fiction,
mystery, drama film directed by David Slade.
In 1984, a young programmer begins to question reality as he
adapts a dark fantasy novel into a video game.
A mind-bending tale with multiple endings.
Stefan Butler, played by Fionn Whitehead.
Peter Butler, played by Craig Parkinson.
Dr. Haynes, played by Alice Lowe.
Mohan Thakur, played by Asim Chaudhry.
Colin Ritman, played by Will Poulter.
Kitty, played by Tallulah Haddon.
Black Mirror: Bandersnatch is a 2018 interactive film in the
science fiction anthology series Black Mirror.
It was written by series creator Charlie Brooker and directed by David Slade.
The film premiered on Netflix on 28 December 2018, its release
date only officially announced the day before.
Netflix did not confirm the interactive nature of Bandersnatch until
its release, though there was much media speculation.
In Bandersnatch, viewers make decisions for the main character, the young programmer Stefan Butler
(Fionn Whitehead), who is adapting a fantasy gamebook into a video game in 1984.
Other characters include Mohan Thakur (Asim Chaudhry) and Colin Ritman (Will Poulter), who work at a
video game company; Stefan's father, Peter (Craig Parkinson); and Stefan's therapist, Dr.
Haynes (Alice Lowe).
A postmodernist work with free will as a central theme, the film was named after a real video game planned for release by
Imagine Software in 1984, the game in turn named after the bandersnatch, a creature of Lewis Carroll's creation.
Brooker and executive producer Annabel Jones were approached by Netflix about making an interactive film
in May 2017, during which time Netflix had several such projects for children underway.
Difficulty in writing the highly non-linear script led to Netflix's creation of a bespoke program called Branch
Manager; the unique nature of the content required adaptations in the platform's use of cache memory.
Bandersnatch was originally to be part of Black Mirror's fifth series, but its lengthy production
led to its release as a standalone film, delaying the fifth series to June 2019.
Critics praised the technical design of the film but
criticised the story's characterisation.
There was mixed commentary about the narrative and the extent
to which viewer choices affected the story.
The film received average rankings in critics' lists of Black Mirror instalments by quality,
but garnered numerous awards and nominations, winning two Primetime Emmy Awards.
A follow-up episode, "Plaything", set in the same universe as Bandersnatch and featuring Poulter and
Chaudhry reprising their roles, was released as part of the series' seventh season in 2025.
Bandersnatch was one of Netflix's early forays into interactive works, but by 2023, Netflix had shifted away from interactive
media towards video games offered by the service  with Netflix citing that the technology had served its purpose.
Netflix delisted several of its interactive works by 2025 with the exception of
Bandersnatch and Unbreakable Kimmy Schmidt: Kimmy vs the Reverend.
Both of these were removed from Netflix in May 2025
as part of a major interface update.
The film explores themes of video game,
technology, choice, time loop, free will.
The tone is emotional and dark and thought_provoking.